alright, answer key class two ready? Here we go ...
Does karma, good karma, which is called merit in the
homework okay, does it necessarily lead to nirvana and Buddhahood?
Does all good karma lead to nirvana and Buddhahood? No okay?
Why? There's dirty good karma okay,
there's the karma you do with a bad
motivation okay, there's a huge question
in Chandrakirti, there's a huge question
in Chandrakirti, ready? So, according to DCI level 4/5 the way to
get a partner, wife or husband, is to help
lonely people. Plant seeds by going to a
nursing home, find an old lady, an old
man, and help them. And I have had one for
20 years okay? Why Geshela, you already have a partner?
I want to keep them, you can't stop, it's
a pyramid scheme ... MLM, yeah okay?
you can't stop okay, to keep the partner going you've got to keep visiting the old
lady okay? So, now there comes a big question in Chandrakirti: if you go to
visit the old lady and you don't love her,
you just use her as your karmic object , you know you try to find the worst one. I
had a guy in Detroit, he raised his hand, he said "Geshela, I
found my old lady", I said "yeah that's
nice", he said "no no I found THE old lady!"
I said, "what do you mean?" He says, "she's poor, she's sick, and she's broke." "Yeah,
poor, broke, and lonely so I can get a partner, money, and good health from one
lady." He was so happy, and it's true okay, I'm sorry, so anyway the question comes
in Chandrakirti: if you visit the old lady with a cold heart,
you just want a boyfriend, you don't care if she dies tomorrow, okay will you get
the boyfriend or not? You will okay, you will. Yeah, but he'll be a selfish son of
a gun okay, you're collecting 2 karmas,
white and black okay? You you will get a
boyfriend, but he will be unpleasant. It is good karma, but it may not lead you to
nirvana or Buddhahood if you don't have the motivation. There's such a thing as
dirty good karma okay? Good karma that has ... comes with the ... you
get the boyfriend but he's selfish okay, or he doesn't have a job and
he expects you to make all the money, something like that, you know this kind
alright. Alright, next question ... in the book the Three Principal Paths you
should understand something important, there's a tradition in the Tsongkapa
lineage that you cannot give the secret teachings [Vajrayana] to a person without a review
of the Lamrim first, even if they pass the eighteen courses it doesn't
matter, you must review the Lamrim with them before they get the secret
teachings, you're not allowed to give the secret teachings without doing a Lamrim
again, which is a summary of the Geshe course.
So, in our Diamond Way course we made it
the first 3 courses, the first 3
courses are actually not Diamond Way, they're a review of the Lamrim,
and a very famous Lamrim called the
Path to Bliss by the First Panchen Lama,
extraordinary poet, extraordinary philosopher, extraordinary, believable okay?
So, and that's the last time Geshe Lotar came here, and during those
teachings he shared a lot of experiences that he had with my teacher okay, that's ...
I think that's the last time he was here, that was ... 16 years ago okay?
Cool? alright. Now, so one of the big secret teachings is called mahamudra
say maha mudra, mahamudra, in Tibetan ... chakya chenpo (pyag rgya chen po)
okay, "mudra" means the seal that a king puts on his letter when he says, "forty
thousand cavalry soldiers should march to Afghanistan and take it over", you know?
it's the old confirmation email, and if you were caught with a seal
resembling the king's seal, you would be killed immediately you see? It means ...
it's his way of signing a paper okay, and you should never ... a king would never be
without his seal, I like to say the American President has a black box, we
call it the black box, and there's a military, a high military officer is always
within ... 20 meters of the American President. That box has the key to send
nuclear missiles around the world, because right now you have only 15
minutes to decide, you have 15 minutes to
send them or not to send them, so they're
just ... they stand outside his bedroom all night, once you become President ... I saw
when Obama came out of the White House he was like "Ahh" you know, "Trump, you got
the box, I don't have the box anymore", you
know? He was so happy you know, why am I
talking about that? It's like the mudra okay, the king, the emperor, must have
their ... nobody can touch it, they must have it with them
okay? So, it became a word to describe the direct perception emptiness okay,
especially the emptiness of your mind okay, it became a word that means the
direct perception emptiness, and then in
Tantra, in the secret teachings, it became
a word for your spiritual partner, okay? Mudra, in the secret teachings, means
your spiritual partner okay, and that's the fastest way to practice the Diamond
Way, if you can find a highly qualified spiritual partner, practice together
with them, that's the fastest way to do the fastest way okay?
it's the highest way, and there are stories in the monastery about Pabongkha's
spiritual partner, very interesting, he had a special cave, and there's all these
stories about this angel who used to walk out of the cave, like people just
run into her, you know like wow,  you know? Buddha had a spiritual partner
called Tilottama okay, and according to
the Diamond Way, he only became
enlightened because he had a spiritual partner and they became enlightened on
the same morning together, so imagine you're sitting together with your
partner, the Sun comes up at Diamond Mountain and with the first rays of
light, you both get enlightened ... that's the real story okay, and you can read it
in the texts, John recovered those texts ...
it's highly secret books of Gyume [Tantric College], I asked
for those books, because my teacher
became the abbot, so I said "you're Abbot
right?" He said, "yeah". I said "give me those books, I want to input them", he said "no!"
And ... we have an input Center about a
hundred yards from the monastery in
Hunsur, so I gave up, I couldn't get those books, twelve highly secret books,
then one day from Hunsur, which is all ladies [in the ACIP input center], the data came, all of it ... all
twelve books you know, I'm like ...
I called them, "how'd you get these books?" They're like, "we know some of the monks."
I'm like, "man, good job!" You know, they didn't do anything bad okay, they just
you know, asked for them ... and ... so the whole story of Tilottama is in those books, and
I translated it and it's in course 17 okay, of the Diamond Way okay?
Tsongkapa had a partner, Tangsha Marmo, the lady with the red hat, and ... that's a
beautiful story which you can read, he was assigned a partner by Manjushri okay,
and he didn't really want one, and that's another story
okay ... but Manjushri said, "look you're going too slow, you need a partner", you know, so that's a
beautiful story okay? You can kind of read that in that big red book if you
look carefully, we even made a painting of her, okay alright ... anyway, why are we
talking about Tantra in the middle of course 1 class 1 of the non-Tantra?
Why are we talking about Mahamudra?
Ya, beautiful! You cannot touch the secret teachings without these 3
attitudes, you will fail, you will fail okay, something bad will happen something
really bad will happen, we had people die here okay, something
bad will happen okay, if you try to practice the secret teachings without
those three attitudes, if your motivation is not: (1) I'm tired, (2) I've got to be a Buddha
got to be a Buddha, (3) I've got to see emptiness directly. If you
don't have those 3 in your heart, you will fail in the second eighteen courses,
you will fail spectacularly, like amazingly, it'll be a real amazing okay?
So ... it's actually, these 3 are
protecting you for when you get to the
higher teachings okay, if you don't have them you cannot practice those teachings
okay? So, Phabongkha Rinpoche, and Tsongkapa, they're trying to sell you ... first grade
Lamrim, you know? And they're telling
you, "if you don't learn addition you
can't learn calculus", you know, see? You won't make it. Got it? You need this stuff.
If you want to become a Buddha, you've
got to have the Three Principal Paths. If
you want to practice Mahamudra, Tantra, with a partner, by the way, why is a
partner called "mudra"? You can never leave them, you see what I mean? it's like the
emperor's stamp okay? You can't ... once you make that
relationship, you should stay with them
okay, until you're enlightened. It
doesn't mean you can't switch partners if it happens okay, but it does mean when
you make that commitment to use that
path, you must have a partner okay, you
can't let go of that ... you can't give up
on that idea okay? If you lose your
partner you should find a new one, a good
one okay?
But you can't give up okay, like you can have fights with your partner, you can
separate for your partner, but you must find your partner okay, you can't give up ...
it's mudra, got it? Okay, and if you don't have the three
principal paths you will lose your partner and bad stuff will happen got it?
Okay, alright ...
yeah, so that's homework question
number 3, what's the relationship
between the three principal paths and
the Great Seal? And the word principal is
misspelled in the homework ... well it happens to the best of us ... okay, question
4, what are the 2 principal causes of
being a Buddha? And we call it, you ready?
method, say method, and wisdom ok? Method and wisdom. They're called the 2 wings
of the bird. If you don't have two wings
you can't fly, okay here's method, here's
wisdom okay? Method is Bodhisattva's training, training
as a bodhisattva, basically. Wisdom is the understanding of
emptiness okay, if you don't have these two you can't fly, you'll never make it.
Okay method, so "method" is a code word for the activities and thinking of a
bodhisattva, "wisdom" is wisdom okay ...
hundred dollars! When's the last time you thought about these things? If you get it
wrong you owe me $100. Nice, dang! He's some expensive dude ... $100.
Yeah ... gewa diyi kyewo kun, sunam yeshe tsok-dzok shing ... oh got it?
Collection of merit and wisdom, okay method and wisdom, got it? Okay, we'll
talk about it ... where does that come from?
For zero dollars ... the 60 Verses of ...[Nagarjuna's 60 Verses on Reasoning] it's
the last of the 60 verses that Nick is translating okay, that prayer you do
every night, alright okay here we go ...
question five, what's the main elements
of method, and what's the main ... what's
inside of method, and what's inside of
wisdom? I'll give you a clue ... split the
three principal paths into those two,
which is which? Where does renunciation
belong? With method,
where does bodhichitta belong? Method. Where does wisdom belong? With wisdom, yay! Okay
you passed question 5. Nick, sorry Tim, I'm on schedule okay ... now, there's a
special teaching called the "bodies of a
Buddha", there's a special teaching called
the "bodies of a Buddha", "kaya" right?
Dharmakaya, Nirmanakaya, Sambhogakaya, kayakaya,
Svabhavakaya, okay, there's lots of kayas, bodies of the buddha, okay and it's
a very very important teaching in Buddhism, is the different bodies of a
Buddha okay? And I'm sorry, you know on the way here I was thinking how do I
explain bodies, they're not bodies, they're not separate bodies okay? It
doesn't mean that, it just means part, okay, Buddha has two parts,
or Buddha has three parts, or Buddha has four parts, okay, so there's three
different ways to teach the kayas, you can teach two,
you can teach three, you can teach four,
okay, I'm gonna do two with you to start
with, okay ready? And it's on your
homework! Number one, say "zuku",
Rupakaya, what does it mean? Yeah, the physical part of a Buddha, the physical
part of a Buddha, okay, the part you can see, touch, okay, that's called Rupakaya,
you want to go deeper? Two parts to the ... there's two bodies inside the
physical body. What ... give me any of them? Give me one. Yeah, those two ... one is called
emanation body, the one you send to
planets okay, the copy of you that
you sent to other planets. You can be a
dog making an old lady happy in Los
Angeles, and you can be an uber driver in
Beijing, Lyft .. doodoo, didi, didi
sorry ... you can be a didi driver in
Beijing at the same time, okay if it
makes people happy, and that's called
emanation body, you have the power to
split your body and serve multiple
people at the same time got it? Easy
right? What's Sambhogakaya? That's called enjoyment body, it just
means your headquarter body, headquarter physical body in Buddha paradise
okay? Headquarter physical body, it has
how many signs? 112, I taught it here
for like a week, but that was a while ago and we got leaky teacups ... 32 major signs,
80 secondary signs, on the Buddha's
body, that body, coke classic, classic body
that's the Sambhogakaya, that's the one that stays in heaven okay?
Then they come here and they look like Seiji, they look like Steven, they look like
Connie, okay that's Nirmanakaya, got it?
Okay, now the other body when you teach
it as
two bodies is called? Dharmakaya, say
Dharmakaya, okay cool,
it also ... you want to go deeper? It also has two parts, which is why you can make
four bodies out of two bodies okay? It also has two parts, number one, the
easy one, is the mental state of a Buddha,
is Jñanadharmakaya okay, Jñanadharmakaya,
the omniscience of a Buddha, the ability to see all things at all
times, okay? Past, present, and future, that
ability is a separate body, body number three so far tonight right? What was
number one? Nirmanakaya, send yourself as a dog to LA, send yourself as a didi
driver to Beijing, and what's the second one? Yeah home body,
you know, paradise body, I ... sometimes I
like to call it paradise body okay, with
the 112 marks okay? Body number three? Is mental, the mental state of a Buddha, can
see all things at all times. Now, body
number four is the most interesting one,
what's it called? The emptiness body, say
Svabhavakaya, "Swa bhawa", Sanskrit doesn't
really have a "v" swa bhawa ... swa bhawa ...
okay, Svabhavakaya okay, emptiness
body ... for $100 and not word ok, you're not ...
if you want to answer it's one dollar ...
tell me what's super cool about the Svabhavakaya, the emptiness body?
Yeah, you have it now, you already have it,
it's your "Buddha nature", it's the ... what's
the Sanskrit word? Word, for $10! Buddha
nature in Sanskrit ... huh? whoa, Tathagata-garbha
say Tathagata garbha okay, "garba" means the womb of a woman, Tathagata
means Buddha, and you already have this womb, every person has it,
you have body number four, you already
have body number four okay, you want to
impress your friends at a cocktail party? I saw a nice cartoon in The New Yorker,
there's this nerdy guy talking to this
lady in a miniskirt and she's ... there at the
cocktail party and then the guys are
trying to impress the girl right? So, and
they ... and in the cartoon she says, "no I
don't want to know your secret mantra" ...
he's just trying to ... okay anyway ,why did I talk about that?
How's that connect to cocktail parties? Oh yeah, you want to impress your friends ...
okay, if you meet a girl at a cocktail party you can say, "do you know that part of you
is already enlightened, you know, you got
25% Buddha in you already", and then she
said "oh wow I'm so impressed, do you want to go out with me?" Ok?
I told Veronica, "you know I'm a real Tibetan grammar nerd, I'm the only one."
She said "oh" ... okay anyway, you're already
25% Buddha okay?
It means you already have emptiness, which means you can change into a Buddha.
Okay, the chew-toy can become a pen
got it? If the stick didn't have
emptiness, the chew toy couldn't become a
pen got it? So you're ... right now we're all
chew toys and you can become a pen, you
can become a Buddha, why? Because you're
not anything from your own side. If you plant the seeds, this can change
okay got it? So that's your blessed fourth body okay?
Why are we talking about that? Homework
question number ... seven. What are the
causes of the two bodies? Yeah, merit and wisdom, you say it every
night right? What's the body that's
created by wisdom? Dharmakaya, Dharma Body
which just means the mind and the emptiness of a Buddha together, because
one is looking at the other, got it? Okay?
The mind of a Buddha and the emptiness of the
Buddha, together are called Dharmakaya,
the ... the body of all things okay, and then
what's the cause of the physical body of
a Buddha? Good, good karma. Good deeds okay.
Sunam .. gewa diyi kyewo kun ... you're hoping I'm finishing the class but I'm not ...
gewa diyi kyewo kun, sunam yeshe tsok-dzok shing, sunam yeshe lejung way, dampa kunyi topar shok. dampa kunyi topar shok ... may all beings achieve the two
two holy bodies okay? That's what we're talking about okay, got it?
Alright .... oh Tim we're gonna make it ... I
think. Which one of the three principal
paths causes each of the bodies? Which
principal path causes the physical body
of a Buddha? Huh? Second one for sure, and also the first one okay? Getting tired of
this life, getting tired of seeing people die around you, and the wish for
enlightenment are causes for the physical body mainly ... that's what you
say in the debate ground when you want to fudge something, "mainly" okay, and then
what's the cause for the wisdom body? The
direct perception emptiness mainly okay,
got it? I'd like to tell you something cool that
happened to me okay, I had this stuff going on all day with Khen Rinpoche, I was
so lucky to live with him, so everything we talked about was
Dharma, and so I would ask him questions constantly and he would try to avoid me,
but I I learned to make momos so he couldn't avoid me, which is the most
delicious Tibetan food, and ... in fact I'm going to make some next week for Geshe Lotar.
I bought the pot, new pot, special one
okay for him, anyway ... I said "Rinpoche what's the connection
between renunciation and bodhichitta?" What do you think he said?
Good! Yeah. Okay, understand? Bodhichitta is just renunciation spread towards
everybody, got it? it's such a cool answer okay?
The second principal path is just the
first principal path aimed at everybody,
got it? The first principle path is aimed at me.
I'm tired ... I'm tired of seeing friends die, I'm tired of being in this kind of
world, okay? Then when you feel like that
for everybody, you reached path number
two, principal path two, got it? cool? Cool ma?
Fēicháng cool. Fēicháng bàng! Okay ...
What's that thing? If a monkey hits on a
typewriter all day, one word will come
out ... that's my Chinese okay ... what are the two
obstacles to Buddhahood? Yeah, one is called mental affliction obstacles okay?
Mental affliction obstacles. The second
one is called? Obstacles to ... omniscience,
okay? Somebody other than Word tell me
why the wording is confusing? For $100.
Somebody who's NOT Word tell me why
these two words are a little confusing.
No, I mean it's a good guess but ... and it's true but it's not what I want.
No...
I can tell it's coming ...
Good! Yeah, think about it ... yeah good. Think about it, in Tibetan the
first obstacle is called "klesha obstacle", but it doesn't mean "obstacle to
reaching kleashas", it means the obstacle which IS kleshas,
you see what I mean? But the traditional
second obstacle is the obstacle to
omniscience, then it's an obstacle to the
goal it's not the obstacle ... so they're
not the same, okay got it? And it's an
easier way to remember it ... I'll say it
again okay, the first kind of obstacle, which is an
obstacle to nirvana is all of your kleshas. The kleshas equal the obstacle,
got it? The kleshas are the problem, got
it? The name of the second obstacle is
omniscience obstacle, and that doesn't
equal anymore.
It means: going to stop you FROM omniscience, you understand? The wording is weird
Okay, if you don't understand ask somebody else, okay ... ha! question 10 yay!
I'm on the last one, I did it. So that means I can do some teacher training
stuff tonight okay, or at least I can start okay .... why was Je Tsongkapa able to
write 10,000 pages of incredibly deep
and difficult explanation of Buddhism? He
cheated! Yeah, he learned how to talk to
Manjushri okay?
in English we call it plagiarism ... it's where you write your book and you steal
everything from DCI or somebody like that okay, he stole everything from
Manjushri and he looked really smart. It
looks like Tsongkapa's really smart, but ...
he got it all from Manjushri, in fact so
well that later he was accused of?
Being Manjushri, okay? Like, he reports to all his friends, the
friends are like "how did you write this thing?" He's like, "I had help from
Manjushri', and then later his close disciples, he said
"I am Manjushri", got it?  He's "really close" to Manjushri, got it? Okay, now you have finished
homework 2.